AJEET KUMAR Singh

PERSONAL DATA

PLACE AND DATE OF BIRTH: Jodhpur, Rajasthan | 13 July 1991

PHONE: +91 88972-65167

EMAIL: ajeetsingh0712[at]gmail[dot]com

WEBPAGE: ajeetksingh.github.io

OBJECTIVE

To strive for excellence in the field of research and development utilizing my technical skills and innovations, aided by my background in machine learning and computer vision, in a best possible way for the fulfillment of organizational goals.

WORK EXPERIENCE

JUL 2016 - CURRENT | Researcher at TCS Innovation Labs, TRDDC, Pune

Responsible for developing deep learning based algorithms to identify and protect the

sensitive information for privacy and security.

JAN 2016 - JUL 2016 | Research Intern at Intel Labs, Bangalore

Responsible for development of deep learning based algorithms for large scale object

recognition, detection and localization in images.

JUN 2013 - DEC 2015 | Research Associate at International Institute of Information and

Technology-Hyderabad

Responsible for development of interactive Optical Character Recognition platform for

web using popular web technologies.

EDUCATION

DEC 2015 MS by Research in Computer Science and Engineering

International Institute of Information Technology, Hydearbad

CGPA: 9.0

Aug 2011 Bachelor of Technology in Computer Engineering

Rajasthan Technical University(Jodhpur Institute of Engineering and Technology)

First Class Honours
PERCENTAGE: 78.16%

MAY 2007 Class XII

Central Academy(Board of Secondary Education, Rajasthan)

PERCENTAGE: 82.62%

MAY 2005 Class X

Central Academy(Board of Secondary Education, Rajasthan)

PERCENTAGE: 89.50%

PROJECTS & PATENTS

JULY 2017 - CURRENT

Secure & Private Deep Learning

Developing private and secure deep learning algorithms for computer vision and deep learning tasks.

- 1. An adversarial learning based algorithm/tool to add subtle noises to the images preventing recognition from predatory machine learning models.
- Adversarial training for deep learning models to prevent attacks such as fast gradient sign method, iterative gradient sign methods.
- 3. Developing basic machine learning models using fully homomorphic encryption algorithm to prevent any privacy leakages using Microsoft SEAL Library.
- 4. To deal with privacy issues evolving from the data, aim is to develop an algorithm which uses very limited data learn the representation.

JUL 2016 - JULY 2017

Data Masking System for Security and Privacy (ONE PATENT FILED IN INDIA, US AND EUROPE)

We developed a data masking system which automatically masks the sensitive contents in a document. This document can be either text or an image.

JAN 2016 - JUL 2016

Large Scale Image Recognition

As part of the PCL team at Intel, my task was to develop deep learning based algorithms for large scale image recognition using popular Residual Networks and its variants.

JUN 2013 - DEC 2015

A Web framework for Optical Character Recognition on Indic Scripts and Languages.

Development of a web-based OCR to provide a state-of-the-art optical character recognition tool to the general public. This web tool contains preprocessing module, script identification module, word recognition module, and an post-processing module. The framework was adaptable to include and evaluate multiple OCRs.

AUG 2015

Script and Language Identification using Recurrent Neural Networks (ACCEPTED AT ICDAR 2015)

In this project, we investigate the utility of popular Recurrent Neural Networks for identification of script and language in document images at word and line level. We achieve the highest accuracy of 99.0% percent in script identification and 94.67% accuracy in language identification. Experiments were done on 12 Indic scripts and 3 Roman-script based languages on 55K document images.

OCT 2015

Script Identification in Multilingual Scene Texts (ACCEPTED AT DAS 2016)

We present an approach for automatically identifying the script of the text localized on the scene images using computer vision. We represent the text images using midlevel strokes based features. We achieved an accuracy of 96.70% on CVSI dataset and benchmark on our own Indian language scene text dataset.

Nov 2014

Billion Word Imputation

This project was done under Machine Learning course requirement under the guidance of Dr. Shailesh Kumar. In this NLP project, our task was to find the missing word in a given sentence as well as its position in the sentence. We found the missing words and their location by finding the co-occurrence consistency calculated from n-gram and skip-grams of the words available in training set.

PUBLICATIONS

ICCV 2019 | FROM STRING TO THINGS: KNOWLEDGE-ENABLED VQA MODEL THAT CAN READ AND REASON.

Ajeet Kumar Singh (TCS Research), Anand Mishra (IIT JODHPUR), Shashank Shekhar (IISc), Anirban Chakraborty (IISc).

ICDAR 2019 OCR-VQA: VISUAL QUESTION ANSWERING BY READING TEXT IN IMAGES.

Anand Mishra (IISc), Shashank Shekhar (IISc), Ajeet Kumar Singh (TCS Research), Anirban Chakraborty (IISc).

CSCML 2019 | EVERYTHING IS IN THE NAME-A URL BASED APPROACH FOR PHISHING DE-

TECTION.

Harshal Tupsamudre (TCS Research), Ajeet Kumar Singh (TCS Research), Sachin Lodha (TCS RESEARCH).

ACCV 2018 | Deep Embedding using Bayesian Risk Minimization with Application to Sketch Recognition.

Ajeet Kumar Singh (TCS Research), Anand Mishra (IISc).

DAS 2016 | A SIMPLE AND EFFECTIVE SOLUTION FOR SCRIPT IDENTIFICATION IN WILD.

Ajeet Kumar Singh (IIIT-H), Anand Mishra (IIIT-H), Pranav Dabral (IIIT-H), C. V.

Jawahar (IIIT-H).

DAS 2016 | MULTILINGUAL OCR FOR INDIC SCRIPTS.

Minesh Mathew (IIIT-H), Ajeet Kumar Singh (IIIT-H), C. V. Jawahar (IIIT-H)

ICDAR 2015 | CAN RNNs Reliably Separate Script and Language at Word and Line

LEVEL?

Ajeet Kumar Singh (IIIT-H), C. V. Jawahar (IIIT-H).

DAS 2014 | TOWARDS ROBUST OCR SYSTEM FOR INDIC SCRIPTS.

Praveen Krishnan (IIIT-H), Naveen Sankaran (IIIT-H), Ajeet Kumar Singh (IIIT-H),

C. V. Jawahar (IIIT-H).

TECNICAL SKILLS

LANGUAGES: C, C++, Python, MATLAB

FRAMEWORKS AND TECHNOLOGY: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Caffe

DATABASES: MySQL

WEB DESIGN: HTML, PHP, JavaScript, AJAX, JQuery

PLATFORMS: Linux, Unix

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Reading.

REFERENCES

AVAILABLE ON REQUEST.